<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0"
         xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/xlink.xsd"
         xml:base="./" xml:id="sect-quick_start-first_steps-create_dashboard"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>Building a dashboard</title>

    <para>A dashboard is basically a page with some KPIs placed on it (plus some
        other additional widgets as we will see later on). There are two different
        ways of creating a page:
    </para>

    <para>Starting as a blank page:
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/ico_NewPage.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>Duplicating an existing page:
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/ico_ClonePage.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>You will find these icons at the top of the page, in the
        administration bar:
    </para>

    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/NewPage_01.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>To create a new page, click on the '<emphasis>Create new
        page</emphasis>' icon:
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/ico_NewPage.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>A form will be shown to fill in some parameters:</para>

    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/NewPage_02.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Page title.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Parent page: Pages are organized in a hierarchical way. This is
                the parent page.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Skin: This will select and specific look'n'feel and CSS stylesheet
                for this page. You can leave the default value.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Envelope: Defines which kind of HTML template will be placed
                around the page layout.
            </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Region layout: This is the template, that is, how regions are
                organized to place the panels inside the page. We can choose any of the
                installed types, for example, "Demo - Default template with
                sliding".
            </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Most of these properties will be discussed in the chapter about
        '<emphasis>Customing look'n'feel</emphasis>'. After creating the page, you
        might realize the page is still not accessible from the left menu but you
        can see it in the combo list in the administration toolbar:
    </para>

    <para>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/toolbar.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </para>

    <para>If you want this page to be shown in the left menu, you can click on
        'Edit content' and then add the newly created page to the list of options
        displayed in the menu.
    </para>

    <table border="0">
        <tr>
            <td valign="top">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/NewPage_05.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </td>

            <td valign="top">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/NewPage_06.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </td>

            <td valign="top">
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/NewPage_07.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </td>
        </tr>
    </table>

    <para>Repeat until the page has all the content and panels required. After
        dropping the panels into the right regions and configuring them, you might
        be able to create dashboards that look like the following one:
    </para>

    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/dashboard_panels.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>As you can see, a dashboard is usually composed by one or more
        instances of the following panel types:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Dashboard &gt; Key Performance Indicator</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Dashboard &gt; Filter &amp; Drill-down</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Navigation &gt; Tree menu</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Navigation &gt; Language menu</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Navigation &gt; Logout panel</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section xml:id="sect-quick_start-first_steps-duplicate_page">
        <title>Duplicating a page</title>

        <para>As mentioned earlier, another way to create new pages is to copy an
            existing one. We can do that via the '<emphasis>Duplicate current
                page</emphasis>' icon which is a much faster way to create pages. After
            clicking on the clone icon located at the toolbar, a page similar to the
            image below will be shown. From there we can select those instances we
            want to duplicate and those we want to keep as is (to reuse).
        </para>

        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/NewPage_10.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>Once finished, press the '<emphasis>Duplicate page</emphasis>'
            button and a brand new page will be created with the same name as the
            original one but starting with the prefix '<emphasis>Copy of</emphasis>'.
            Notice that if a panel instance is reused then any changes made to it will
            be reflected on all the pages where such instance is being used. this is a
            cool feature when we are defining for instance our navigation menus since
            we can define a single<emphasis>'Tree menu'</emphasis>panel and then
            configure all the pages to display the same menu instance.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sect-quick_start-first_steps-filter">
        <title>Configuring filter and drill-down</title>

        <para>The '<emphasis>Filter &amp; Drill-down</emphasis>' panel allows for
            the quick definition of dynamic forms that will allow us to navigate
            troughout the data displayed by the dashboard. Once an instance of the
            '<emphasis>Filter &amp; Drill-down</emphasis>' panel is dropped on the
            oage we just have to select the '<emphasis>Edit content</emphasis>' option
            from the panel menu. After that, a popup window similar to the following
            will be displayed:
        </para>

        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/EditDataFilter_01.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>This is a filter configuration panel where we can set the filter
            behaviour. Let's focus first on the middle bottom part of the screen: the
            <emphasis>Data provider's property table</emphasis>, which lists the
            properties of ALL the data providers referred by the KPIs on the page. For
            example, if we are building a sales dashboard and all its KPIs are built
            on top of the same data provider called '<emphasis>Sales dasboard
                demo</emphasis>' then the system lists all the
            <emphasis><emphasis>data
                properties of the '</emphasis>Sales dashboard demo
            </emphasis>
            ' provider.
            Hence, only the properties we select as '<emphasis>Visible</emphasis>'
            will be part of the filter form. Aditionally, we can enable the drill-down
            feature for each property. If enabled then the system will redirect to the
            target page when the property is selected on the filter form. Below is an
            screenshot of the filter panel of the '<emphasis>Sales dashboard
                demo</emphasis>'.
        </para>

        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/sales_dashboard_filter.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>As you can see the form is composed by all the visible properties
            selected. For each property the system reads its configuration by asking
            the underlying data provider. For label type properties a drop-down list
            is displayed, containing as options all the disctinct values of the data
            provider's column. When the user submits a change on the filter form then
            the following operations are carried out by the dashboard visualization
            engine:
        </para>

        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>It reads the data sets for the target data providers. A data
                    provider is in the target set if it contains the selected filter
                    property.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>It applies a filtering algorithm in memory on the target data.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>If drill-down is enabled for the selected property then the
                    target page is set as current and the steps #1 and #2 are repeated
                    again.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>Finally, after filtering, all the sensible KPIs are updated in order to
                    display the filtered data. By sensible, we mean a KPI which is
                    displaying data that is being filtered.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

        <para/>
    </section>

</section>
